Finding Aid for Vice President for Development (University of Michigan) Publications, 1921-ongoing (bulk 1953-2004)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Vice President for Development (University of Michigan) publications 1921-[ongoing], 1953-2004
University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development.
5 linear feet
0394, Bimu, B6, 2
University of Michigan office overseeing institutional development and fundraising activities. Includes miscellaneous brochures, directories, newsletters, organizational charts, reports, and statistics of the Vice-President for Development and the Office of University Relations and Development; also includes brochures and newsletters from the various financial campaigns such as the Campaign for Michigan-A Heritage for Leadership, the Annual Giving Program, and the Campaign for Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the Vice President for Development (donor no. 3813 ). Publications also were received from the Development Council (donor no. 3576 ).
The publications are open without restriction.
For historical note, please consult manuscript finding aid immediately preceding publications finding aid.
The University of Michigan. Vice President for Development Publications (5 linear feet) include annual reports, brochures, directories, ephemera including flyers, invitations, posters, and programs, histories, manuals, newsletters, and reports. These publications are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Major Campaign Publications. The bulk of the publications document the day-to-day activities of the Development Office. Researchers will also find publications detailing the Development Council, the Michigan Alumni Fund, Office of Trusts and Bequests, the Presidential Societies, and major capital campaigns, including the $55 Million Program to Ensure the Vital Margin, a Heritage of Leadership: Campaign for Michigan, the Campaign for Michigan, and the Michigan Difference.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development.; Campaign for Michigan-A Heritage for Leadership.; University of Michigan. Annual Giving Program.; Campaign for Michigan.; University of Michigan. Office of University Relations and Development.; Legacy of commitment to scholarship.; University of Michigan honor roll.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Office of University Relations and Development.
Genre Terms:
Brochures.; Directories.; Newsletters.; Organizational charts.; Reports.; Statistics.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Vice President for Development. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications series (1.5 linear feet) includes an annual report, brochures, calendars of development events, directories of the development staff, manuals on the use of the development database Development/Alumni/Constituent System (DAC), and organizational charts detailing responsibilities of the development staff. There are printouts of e-mail announcements covering the period from 1995 to 2003 and a printout of the website from 2000. There is a 1986 history of named professorships (as opposed to a history of development) entitled A Legacy of Commitment to Scholarship: Named Faculty Positions at the University of Michigan. This publication gives brief sketches of the donors of endowed chairs, as well as the faculty members who held the chairs when the history was written. Also located in this series is a videotape (VHS: 12 minutes) documenting the history of development at the University of Michigan. The Development History will be found under the heading "videotapes" in Box 2.
  There are several newsletters published by the Vice President for Development office. The Development Network News (1991-2001) is an e-mail newsletter (printouts) describing classes provided for the development staff of the university to aid them in their work. Newsletter of Development Programs (1989-1992) is an outreach tool focusing on stories of major donations given to the university. Earlier issues of this publication will be found in the Major Campaign Publications series under the Heritage of Leadership campaign. Leaders & Best (1998-ongoing) is used to inform the public of major contributions to the university. Earlier issues of this publication will be found under Campaign for Michigan in the Major Campaign Publications series.
  There are extensive reports discussing the DAC, long-range planning, endowment and student loan funds, and investment in private support. Under the heading "statistics" researchers will find statistics about university alumni (1984) and comparative data for the Big 10 and other peer institutions (1988).
  - Annual Reports
    - Annual Report of Voluntary Support, 7/1/85-6/30/86 (Box 1)
  - Brochures 1924-1994, undated (Box 1)
  - Calendars
    - Development Events Calendar, 1987-1991 (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Development Staff Directory, 1992-1998, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Maize Pages, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Ephemera, includes flyers and invitations 1992, 1997-1998, undated (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - A Legacy of Commitment to Scholarship: Named Faculty Positions at the University of Michigan, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Donor/Alumni Names and DAC, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Guide to Services, 1981, undated (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Development Network News, printouts, 1991-2001, 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Leaders & Best
      - 1998-2001 (Box 1)
      - 2002-ongoing (Box 1)
    - Newsletter of Development Programs, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Private Giving, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Stewardship at Michigan, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Volunteer Briefing, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - Organizational Charts
    - University Relations and Development, undated (Box 1)
  - Printouts
    - E-mail 1995-2003, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Website 2000 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Alumni/Donor Data Base Statistics, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Alumni Giving Programs, 1988 (Box 2)
    - A Compilation of Selected Independent Rankings of Undergraduate, Graduate and Professional Programs in Colleges and Universities, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Development/Alumni/Constituent System, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Development/Alumni/Constituent (DAC) Project Report to the Executive Computing Committee, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Development Expense History, 1984-1991, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Development Long-Range Planning Preliminary Review and Recommendations, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Development Study for the University of Michigan, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Development Study for the University of Michigan and the American Academy, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Endowment and Student Loan Funds of the University of Michigan, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Item for Information, 1982-1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Report to the Vice President for University Relations and Development, 1975 (Box 2)
    - U-M Investment in Private Support for the 1980s, undated (Box 2)
  - Speeches
    - Enriching a Heritage of Leadership by Harold Shapiro, 1982 (Box 2)
    - The Legacy of Martin Luther King, Jr.: A Call to Greatness, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Statistics
    - Comparative Data for Big 10 and Other Selected Institutions, 1988 (Box 2)
    - The University of Michigan Alumni, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Surveys
    - Alumni Recognition: Survey of Programs, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Videotapes
    - Development History, (VHS: 12 minutes), undated (Box 2)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs, and organizations within the Vice President for Development. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
  The Sub-Unit Publications series (1.5 linear feet) includes publications from the Development Council, Michigan Alumni Fund, Office of Trusts and Bequests, and the Presidential Societies. Documenting the Development Council are annual reports covering the period from 1953-1957 and 1962/63. There are newsletters entitled Development Newsletter (1953-1954), Developments (1954-1966), and Development Council Memo (1972-1979). These newsletters all document donors to the university and various research activities benefited by their contributions.
  The Michigan Alumni Fund is described through the Annual Report (1953-1968) and The University of Michigan Honor Roll (1969-1982). These reports include alphabetical lists of donors within various giving categories. The Alumni Fund was originally incorporated in 1920 to raise funds to help promote and develop university programs. Researchers should consult the 1924 report titled The University of Michigan Alumni Fund for more information about this early development campaign. It is cataloged separately (call number FImu H1a).
  The Office of Trusts and Bequests is documented through brochures, a manual for the planned giving staff to aid them as they assist future donors, and a 1992 report discussing gifting opportunities through life income arrangements, estate planning, and gifts of real property. The newsletters A Periodic Bulletin Regarding Trust & Bequest Programs at the University of Michigan (1992-1993) and Michigan Matters (1992-1999) chronicle individuals who have established trusts, unitrusts, donor pooled income funds, etc. and how their generosity benefits both them and the university.
  The publications describing the Presidential Societies include brochures, invitations, and programs from the Angell, Henry P. Tappan, and John Monteith Societies. The 2002 cookbook entitled Tailgater's Cookbook is also found here.
  - Alumni/Donor Computer Systems Committee 1987 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Giving Fund 1979, undated (Box 2)
  - Alumni Giving Programs 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - Capital Campaign Office, (School of Music Prospectuses) undated (Box 2)
  - Corporate Relations undated (Box 2)
  - Corporate and Foundation Relations 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - Deferred Giving Program undated (Box 2)
  - Development Council
    - Annual Reports 1953-1957, 1962/63 (Box 2)
    - Brochures
      - Miscellaneous undated (Box 2)
      - Education Shall Forever Be Encouraged, circa 1958 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Development Council Memo, 1972-1979, undated (Box 2)
      - Development Newsletter, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - Developments, 1954-1966 (Box 2)
  - Development Education Program 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Foundation Relations 1985 (Box 2)
  - Gift Processing Task Force 1992-1997 (Box 2)
  - Investment Office 1992 (Box 2)
  - Long-Range Planning Committee for Development 1987 (Box 2)
  - Major Gifts Committee 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Alumni Fund
    - Annual Reports
      - Annual Report, 1953/54-1968, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - The University of Michigan Honor Roll, 1969-1982, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Brochures 1921, undated (Box 3)
  - Michigan Benefactors 1974-1983, undated (Box 3)
  - Office of Trusts and Bequests
    - Brochures undated (Box 3)
    - Manuals
      - Planned Giving at Michigan, undated (Box 3)
    - Newsletters
      - Michigan Matters, 1992-1999 (Box 3)
      - A Periodic Bulletin Regarding Trust & Bequest Programs at the University of Michigan, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - Trust and Bequest Program, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Planned Giving Program undated (Box 3)
  - Presidential Societies
    - Brochures and Programs 1990, 1993, 2002, undated (Box 3)
    - Cookbooks
      - Tailgater's Cookbook, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Individual Societies
      - Angell Society 1989, 1999 (Box 3)
      - Henry P. Tappan Society undated (Box 3)
      - John Monteith Society undated (Box 3)
  - President's Advisory Group on Planning 1991 (Box 3)
  - Presidents Club 1975-1978, 1983/84, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - President's Weekend 1985-1995 (Box 3)
  - Seminar Series for Women of Michigan 1994, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Task Force on Centennial Fund-raising 1983 (Box 3)
  - Task Force on Increasing Women's Involvement in Development 1994 (Box 3)
  - University Relations 1965, undated (Box 3)
  - University Seminars 1990 (Box 3)
- Major Campaign Publications
  - $55 Million Program to Ensure the Vital Margin (1965-1967)
    - Brochures
      - Guide to Objectives, 1965, undated (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous 1964-1967 (Box 4)
      - Specific Projects
        - Advanced Management Center, 1966 (Box 4)
        - More Room for Books...More Room for Readers: Proposed Graduate Library, undated (Box 4)
        - Great Lakes Research, 1966 (Box 4)
        - Institute for Social Research, undated (Box 4)
        - A World Outlook on Legal Education, undated (Box 4)
        - Preserving the Michigan Story: A Building for the Michigan Historical Collections for this Unique Resource, undated (Box 4)
        - The First Residential College for Undergraduates, 1966 (Box 4)
        - School of Natural Resources, 1966 (Box 4)
        - A New Theater for the University of Michigan and a Regional Center for the Performing Arts, 1967 (Box 4)
        - The University Concert Hall on the North Campus, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Invitations undated (Box 4)
    - Manuals
      - The Gifts...and How to Get Them, undated (Box 4)
      - A Handbook for Committee Members, undated (Box 4)
    - Newsletters
      - Fifty-Five for Michigan, 1966 (Box 4)
      - The $55 Million Bulletin, 1966-1968 (Box 4)
      - The Vital Margin, 1965-1967 (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - Final Report to the President and Regents, 1967 (Box 4)
      - Pocket Guide to Objectives, 1965 (Box 4)
      - Selected Needs and Opportunities, 1965 (Box 4)
  - A Heritage of Leadership: Campaign for Michigan (1983-1989)
    - Brochures undated (Box 4)
    - Brochures, Invitations, and Programs for Individual Projects
      - Center for Champions, undated (Box 4)
      - The Power Center for the Performing Arts, 1989 (Box 4)
      - Replacement Hospital Project 1983 (Box 4)
      - School of Music undated (Box 4)
      - School of Business Administration undated (Box 4)
      - Schools and Colleges 1983-1987 (Box 4)
      - Tappan Hall undated (Box 4)
      - Willard H. Dow Laboratory 1989 (Box 4)
    - Fact Sheets, regarding Schools and Colleges undated (Box 4)
    - Flyers undated (Box 4)
    - Newsletters
      - Annual Tax Update, 1986 (Box 4)
      - Briefing, 1988-1990 (Box 4)
      - Campaign Briefing, 1984-1987, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Campaign for Michigan, 1986-1988 (Box 4)
    - Organization Charts
      - Volunteer Organization, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Programs 1983-1989 (Box 4)
    - Prospectuses
      - The Chemical Sciences Project: A Notebook of Commemorative Naming Opportunities, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - Campaign Plan, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
      - Fund-raising Projects Proposed by Schools, Colleges, and Other Units, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Partners in Leadership 1989, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Campaign for Michigan: M Campaign (1992-1997)
    - Brochures
      - Miscellaneous 1993-1995, undated (Box 5)
      - Profiles, 1991, undated (Box 5)
      - Schools and Colleges 1992-1993 (Box 5)
    - Brochures for Specific Projects
      - East Engineering Building Renovation 1993 (Box 5)
      - Hill Auditorium undated (Box 5)
      - School of Education undated (Box 5)
    - Case Statements
      - A Heritage of Leadership: The Challenge of Change, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Letterheads undated (Box 5)
    - Newsletters
      - Leaders & Best: Campaign for Michigan, 1992-1997, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - M Campaign: Volunteer Briefing, 1992-1997 (Box 5)
    - Notebooks
      - Volunteer Notebook, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Programs and Invitations 1991-1996, undated (Box 5)
    - Reports
      - Michigan Screening Program
        - Report: Phases I & II, October 1990- June 1992, 1992 (Box 5)
        - Report: Phases I, II & III, 1990-1993, 1993 (Box 5)
      - The Post-Campaign Planning Committee Final Report, 1995 (Box 5)
      - Report on Campaign Planning: Meeting of President's Advisory Group, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Steering Committee Agenda Papers, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Strategic Plan: The Campaign for Michigan, 1990-1997, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Specific Campaign Events
      - Kick-Off 1992 (Box 5)
      - Mid-Campaign Event 1994 (Box 5)
      - Campaign Close 1997 (Box 5)
    - Post Campaign Planning Committee 1995 (Box 5)
  - The Michigan Difference 2004-
    - Brochures 2004- (Box 5)